Samuel Franklin Emmons Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Samuel Franklin Emmons Papers 1725-1914 (bulk 1861-1911)
MSS23747
Emmons, Samuel Franklin, 1841-1911
14,000 items
41 containers plus 1 oversize
16.4 linear feet
1 microfilm reel
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Geologist. Diaries and field notes, letterbooks, correspondence, family papers, subject files, photographs, printed matter, and miscellaneous material relating chiefly to Emmons's family and his career as a geologist.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bartlett, Suzanne Earle Ogden-Jones Emmons, 1861-1954. Suzanne Earle Ogden-Jones Emmons Bartlett papers. 1897-1913.; Emmons family.; Emmons, Samuel Franklin, 1841-1911.; Evans, N. Henry--Correspondence.; King, Clarence, 1842-1901.; Markoe, Sophie D. Sophie D. Markoe papers. 1852-1911.
Organizations
Geological Survey (U.S.); United States Geological Exploration of the Fortieth Parallel (1867-1881)
Subjects
Formations (Geology); Geology.; Mineral industries.; Mines and mineral resources.
Places
West (U.S.)--Discovery and exploration.
Occupations
Geologists.
Provenance
The papers of Samuel Franklin Emmons, geologist, were given to the Library of Congress by his widow, Suzanne Earle Ogden-Jones Emmons Bartlett, in 1947-1948, following a fire in the facility where the papers had been stored that damaged a considerable amount of the material. In 1958, her daughter, Mrs. Armistead Peter III, gave additional papers from her mother's estate.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Samuel Franklin Emmons are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on one reel. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1841, Mar. 29 Born, Boston, Mass.
1861 Graduated, Harvard College, Boston, Mass.
1862 1865 Attended Ecole Imperiale des Mines, France
1867 1877 Member, United States Geological Exploration of the Fortieth Parallel
1872 Exposed a diamond swindle in the Vermillion Creek Basin, Wyo.
1876 Married Weltha Anita Steeves
1877 Joined American Institute of Mining Engineers
1879 1909 Geologist, United States Geological Survey
1882 Published Abstract of a Report upon the Geology and Mining Industry of Leadville, Lake Co., Colorado. Extract from the Annual Report of the Director of the U.S. Geological Survey-1880-81. Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office
1885 Published with G. F. Becker Geological Sketches of the Precious Metal Deposits of the Western United States, with Notes on Lead Smelting at Leadville. Extract from the Tenth Census of the United States, Vol. XIII "Statistics and Technology of the Precious Metals." Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office
1889 Married Sophie Dallas Markoe
1891 General secretary, 5th International Geological Congress
1903 President, Geological Society of America Married Suzanne Earle
1911, Mar. 28 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Samuel Franklin Emmons (1841-1911) span the years 1725-1913, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1861-1911. The collection consists of diaries and field notes, letterbooks, correspondence, family papers, subject files, financial records, photographs, printed matter, and scrapbooks. Some material is in French, German, Spanish, and Italian. The collection was damaged by fire and water prior to being received by the Library and much of it is in fragile or decayed condition.
The papers treat Emmons's education, personal life, and business ventures, but the focus is on his explorations in the western United States, on geological formations and mines and mining, and on the United States Geological Survey that Emmons cofounded with Clarence King (1842-1901). Prominent in the collection are files pertaining to the United States Geological Exploration of the Fortieth Parallel, 1867-1876. There is considerable family material, including correspondence with his uncle, N. Henry Evans, and papers relating to his wives, Sophie D. Markoe and Suzanne Earle Odgen-Jones Emmons Bartlett.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in nine series:
Diaries and Field Notes, 1861-1910
Letterbooks, 1884-1909
Correspondence, 1861-1912
Financial Records, 1867-1911
Subject File, 1725-1912
Sophie D. Markoe Papers, 1852-1911
Suzanne Earle Ogden-Jones Emmons Bartlett Papers, 1897-1914
Scrapbooks, 1871-1905
Oversize, 1866-1907
Container List
- Diaries and Field Notes, 1861-1910 (Box 1-6)
  Diary volumes and field notes.
  Diaries are arranged chronologically. Field notes are arranged by expedition.
  - Diaries (Box 1)
    - 1861-1870, (6 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1871-1886, (8 folders) (Box 2)
      Diary of 1872 is available on microfilm. Shelf no. 16,978
    - 1887-1897, (6 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1898-1905, (6 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1907-1910, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Field notes (Box 5)
    - Expeditions (Box 5)
      - 1869-1872, (3 folders) (Box 5)
      - 1872-1879, (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Acari mines, 1897 (Box 6)
    - Dolliver Mountain Co., 1902 (Box 6)
    - Unidentified, 1907-1908, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
- Letterbooks, 1884-1909 (Box 7-8)
  General letterbooks containing copies of incoming and outgoing correspondence on business, financial, and legal matters.
  General letterbooks are arranged chronologically. Letterbook for the New Pedrara Onyx Co. and an index are filed at the end of the series.
  - General (Box 7)
    - 1884-1900, (4 folders) (Box 7)
    - 1909 (Box 8)
  - New Pedrara Onyx Co., 1893-1898 (Box 8)
  - Index, undated (Box 8)
  - Letters from letterbooks, 1893-1897, undated (Box 8)
- Correspondence, 1861-1912 (Box 8-16)
  Letters sent and received by Emmons and family members.
  Correspondence of Samuel Franklin Emmons is arranged chronologically. Correspondence of other Emmons family members is arranged alphabetically by name of family member.
  - Emmons, Samuel Franklin (Box 8)
    - 1861-1875, (4 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1876-1885, (6 folders) (Box 9)
    - 1886-1891, (6 folders) (Box 10)
    - 1891-1893, (6 folders) (Box 11)
    - 1894-1902, (6 folders) (Box 12)
    - 1903-1909, (7 folders) (Box 13)
    - 1910-1912, undated, (6 folders) (Box 14)
    - Incomplete letters and loose pages, 1884-1910, undated, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Fragments, undated (Box 15)
  - Other family members (Box 15)
    - Brewster, Frank, 1886-1888, undated (Box 15)
    - Brewster, G. W. Wales, 1864, 1894-1902 (Box 15)
    - Brewster, Paul O., 1892 (Box 15)
    - Brewster, Robert G., 1889, 1898-1909 (Box 15)
    - Bullitt, James F., 1899 (Box 15)
    - Emmons, Elise, 1888 (Box 15)
    - [Emmons?], Elizabeth and Emilie, 1897, 1907 (Box 15)
    - Emmons, N. Henry (Box 15)
      - 1861-1862, (2 folders) (Box 15)
      - 1862-1865, 1897-1902, undated (Box 16)
    - [Emmons?], Nelson, 1898 (Box 16)
- Financial Records, 1867-1911 (Box 16-20)
  Expense records, account books, ledgers, and miscellany.
  Arranged by type of material and chronologically thereunder.
  - Expense record books, 1893-1905, (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Ledgers (Box 16)
    - 1878-1891 (Box 16)
    - 1892-1909 (Box 17)
  - Miscellany (Box 17)
    - 1867-1885, (3 folders) (Box 17)
    - 1886-1893, (5 folders) (Box 18)
    - 1894-1911, undated, (6 folders) (Box 19)
  - Petty cash books, 1878-1891 (Box 20)
- Subject File, 1725-1912 (Box 20-37)
  Reports and writings, printed matter, photographs, educational and training materials, financial and legal records, congressional hearing records, commemorative material, address and appointment books, genealogical and social records, drawings and music.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material or topic.
  - Autographs, undated (Box 20)
  - Address books and cards, undated (Box 20)
  - Appointments, 1883-1906 (Box 20)
  - Awards, 1882-1903 (Box 20)
  - Book lists, undated, (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - Calling cards, undated (Box 20)
  - Diamond Discovery of 1872, by Emmons, undated (Box 21)
  - Drawings, undated See Oversize (Box 21)
  - Ecole Imperiale des Mines, France (Box 21)
    - Cours de Machines, by [?] Callon, 1858, (3 folders) (Box 21)
    - Graduation certificate, 1864 (Box 21)
    - Miscellany, 1862-1865 (Box 21)
  - European trip, 1861-1862 (Box 22)
  - Family heights and weights, 1906-1908 (Box 22)
  - Genealogical material (Box 22)
    - Correspondence, 1725, 1847, 1873, 1893-1904, undated (Box 22)
    - Notebook, 1892 (Box 22)
    - Notes, undated See also Oversize, (3 folders) (Box 23)
  - International Congress of Geologists (Box 23)
    - 3rd Congress, 1885 (Box 23)
    - 5th Congress, 1888-1891 (Box 23)
  - Legal papers, 1872-1911, undated (Box 23)
  - Maps, 1893-1907, undated See also Oversize (Box 24)
  - Mines and mining (Box 24)
    - Leadville, Colo. (Box 24)
      - Miscellany, 1894-1896, undated (Box 24)
      - Specimens, undated (Box 24)
    - Mexican mines, 1896-1903, undated (Box 24)
    - Miscellany, 1866-1867, 1894, undated See also Oversize (Box 24)
    - New Pedrara Onyx Co. (Box 24)
      - Correspondence, 1893-1895 (Box 24)
      - Financial records, 1894 (Box 24)
      - Maps, undated See Oversize (Box 25)
      - Minutes, 1893-1900, undated (Box 25)
      - Miscellany, 1866, 1873-1906, undated (Box 25)
  - Musical scores, undated (Box 25)
  - Notes, 1862, 1872, 1894, undated (Box 25)
  - Office of the Chief of Engineers (Box 25)
    - Correspondence, 1873-1876 (Box 25)
    - Financial records, 1871-1876, (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - U.S. Geological Exploration of the Fortieth Parallel, 1867-1876, (2 folders) (Box 25)
  - Photographs (Box 26)
    - Bivouvac, undated (Box 26)
    - European art and architecture album, undated (Box 26)
    - Family, undated (Box 26)
    - Freiburg, Germany, 1864 (Box 26)
    - Miscellany, 1864, 1879, undated See also Oversize, (1 folder); (6 folders) (Box 26, Box 27)
    - Morse, W. G., 1872, 1894, undated (Box 27)
    - Washington, D.C., group portrait, 1887 (Box 27)
  - Printed matter (Box 28)
    - Books, 1868-1905, undated, (2 folders) (Box 28)
    - Miscellany, 1864-1911, undated, (2 folders) (Box 29)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1864-1911, undated (Box 29)
    - Pamphlets and booklets (Box 29)
      - About Emmons, 1911-1912 (Box 29)
      - By Emmons, 1890-1906 (Box 29)
      - On geology and mining (Box 29)
        - In English, (1 folder); (5 folders); (4 folders); (1 folders) (Box 29, Box 30, Box 31, Box 32)
        - In French, (3 folders) (Box 32)
        - In German, (4 folders); (3 folders) (Box 33, Box 34)
        - In Spanish and Italian, (1 folder) (Box 34)
  - Reports (Box 34)
    - Economic Geology of the Cananea Mountains, 1908 (Box 34)
    - Miscellany, 1876, 1885, undated, (1 folder) (Box 34, Box 35)
    - Raft River Mountains (incomplete), undated (Box 35)
  - United States Geological Survey (Box 35)
    - Director’s report, 1881 (Box 35)
    - Financial records, 1885, undated (Box 35)
    - King, Clarence, 1873-1902, undated See also Oversize (Box 35)
    - Miscellany, 1881-1904 See also Oversize (Box 35)
    - Office operation, 1903, undated (Box 35)
    - Publications, 1886 (Box 36)
    - Twentieth-anniversary dinner, 1904 (Box 36)
  - Washington Casino Association (Box 36)
    - Board of directors, 1884 (Box 36)
    - Correspondence (Box 36)
      - 1883-1891, undated, (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 36, Box 37)
    - Financial records, 1883-1886, undated (Box 37)
    - Legal papers, 1883 (Box 37)
    - Miscellany, undated (Box 37)
    - Stockholders’ meetings, 1883-1888 (Box 37)
- Sophie D. Markoe Papers, 1852-1911 (Box 37-40)
  Autographs, quotations, and birthday greetings collected by Markoe and her correspondence, diary, financial records, and society notices.
  - Autograph book, 1883-1885 (Box 37)
  - Birthday book, 1881-1885 (Box 37)
  - Books of quotations (Box 38)
    - 1876-1880, (3 folders) (Box 38)
    - 1880-1888, (3 folders) (Box 39)
  - Correspondence, 1876-1895, undated (Box 39)
  - Diary, 1895 (Box 40)
  - Essays from the London Times, 1852 (Box 40)
  - Financial records, 1885, 1896 (Box 40)
  - Markoe, Mary G., 1903-1911, undated (Box 40)
  - Society notices, 1891-1894, undated (Box 40)
- Suzanne Earle Ogden-Jones Emmons Bartlett Papers, 1897-1914 (Box 40-41)
  Correspondence, financial records, calling cards, invitations, and miscellany.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Calling cards, undated (Box 40)
  - Correspondence, 1897-1913, (2 folders) (Box 40)
  - Financial records, 1906-1913, undated (Box 41)
  - Invitations, 1910, undated (Box 41)
  - Miscellany, 1910-1914, undated (Box 41)
- Scrapbooks, 1871-1905 (Box 41)
  One volume covers the United States Geological Exploration of the Fortieth Parallel with general volumes and newspaper clippings.
  General volumes and newspaper clippings are arranged chronologically.
  - United States Geological Exploration of the Fortieth Parallel, 1871-1879 (Box 41)
  - General, 1889-1905, (2 vols.) (Box 41)
  - Loose clippings, 1886, undated (Box 41)
- Oversize, 1866-1907 (Box OV 1)
  Drawings, genealogical notes, maps, photographs, and a presidential proclamation.
  Arranged and described according to the series and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Subject File (Box OV 1)
    - Drawings, undated (Container 21) (Box OV 1)
    - Genealogical material (Box OV 1)
      - Notes, undated (Container 23) (Box OV 1)
    - Maps, 1893-1907 (Container 24) (Box OV 1)
    - Mines and mining (Box OV 1)
      - Miscellany, plate Chinese coal-bearing rocks, 1866 (Container 24) (Box OV 1)
      - New Pedrara Onyx Co., map, undated (Container 24) (Box OV 1)
    - Photographs, miscellany, undated (Container 26) (Box OV 1)
    - United States Geological Survey (Box OV 1)
      - King, Clarence, genealogical chart, 1891 (Container 35) (Box OV 1)
      - Miscellany, proclamation by President Benjamin Harrison, 1890 (Container 35) (Box OV 1)